hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream
74.1 on March 6
2024 we're here discussing narrative
fallacy in Clinical Psychology and
Psychiatry with Alexi tolinski and
guests so first there will be a
presentation then we'll have a
discussion and look forward to everyone
sharing what they have to say on that so
thank you Lexi first to you for um
organizing this and and catalyzing it
and also for the presentation so thank
you go for
it well thank you Daniel I'm most
grateful to act benr Institute and you
personally for hosting us and your
commentary uh and advice like to thank
wonderful panel members from many
different countries who found the time
and expressed interest in in being here
and uh to everyone watching us and
YouTube
um I'm hopeful to clarify from the
get-go uh um the terminology because a
lot of uh people I talk to reacted to
the word fallacy but uh as if I'm trying
to kind of talk about truth and
psychoanalysis or point out some
inaccuracies this is not my intent at
all or to the word narrative because
it's a vast topic and Linguistics are
involved on tropology I just wanted to
clarify that narrative fallacy the two
words together is specific technical
term uh uh introduced by in 2007 and so
I'll try to keep this discussion sort of
on the ground under the hood and uh
we'll I'll illustrate this concept then
I will Define it uh hopefully we'll
discuss it from the standpoint of
neuropsychology active inference and
then move on to clinical applications
and I very much look forward to a
discussion and so I'll proceed um this
is the preprint of the paper possibly
some of you had a chance to look at
it um and uh if you don't mind I'll
start with this
example what I'll ask everyone to do is
to try to memorize a list of words that
I'll give you and observe how you feel
while doing so and we'll do it a couple
of times is that okay sure all right so
here we go so
um Magnolia
1964 firefighters Club Chicago Jazz
10 what was the last one
10 um okay now I will do the same thing
and uh I will present this to you in a
slightly different format
okay on a cold winter day uh in 1964 a
jazz clot Magnolia in Chicago caught on
fire the firefighters were on the scene
within 10
minutes uh for most of us it is uh uh a
little bit easier to uh retain the
second format and uh you know we'll talk
today about why this is and what's going
on here and then I'm just using this as
an illustration the example is from the
repeated battery for neuropsychological
assessment rband I modified it slightly
but this is sort of what we'll be
talking about uh usually in these
conversations uh Miller comes up and
Mark SS calls this a Miller's law I mean
I think it's a model it's well
established and uh uh researched but
Miller wrote a famous paper in 1956
called the magical number 7 plus or
minus 2 he uh stated that we can process
about uh seven units of information uh
plusus two on average and uh it's
important important that he didn't say
seven digits he said seven
chunks
um uh so I wanted to say that uh you
know he already in 1956 talked about
chunking and uh to by any chance if
somebody's not familiar with the term
when you hear a phone number uh uh the
area code is usually you know we
memorize it as one unit information so
I'm in Maryland and 301 is a frequent
area code here it doesn't take three
units of information it takes just one
um the interesting kicker is that if we
move from sort of random uh pieces of
data to uh sentences then our span
immediately doubles it becomes
um just give me one
second uh all right so um and we'll talk
about possibly why this is so moving
away from memory examples which is a bit
artificial I just wanted to illustrate
it
experientially uh narrative fallacy is
about how we process information how we
uh hear speech of others how we read and
it refers to our uh limited ability to
look at sequences of facts without
weaving an explanation into them or
equivalently forcing a logical link and
arrow of relationship upon them uh if we
describe it slightly differently we can
say that narrative fallacy is quite
simply connecting the dots in to a story
form when we don't have the data that
these dots are indeed connected to each
other Daniel kanaman makes a slightly
broader statements uh he he says that we
tend to think in stories uh not
statistically in our conscious minds and
all of that is pretty much about the
same
thing what is related to this
conversation is the concept of work in
memory and bear with me to whom it's
trivial but it is also a a concept and a
model not a fact and uh uh it relies on
an assumption that there exist a system
in the brain mind which we use to
temporarily store maintain and
manipulate information particularly on
complex tasks so if I were to ask you to
multiply in your mind 17 * 69 then
presumably you'll be using your work in
memory to do that and one of the leading
researchers in this field is Ellen
battley uh he and and his uh lab are
working on uh updated model which will
hopefully be published this year
but you know he makes a point stating in
in some textbooks that uh relationship
between working memory long-term memory
action perception semantics is complex
flexible and interactive so these
systems are
intertwined if I may you know use a
computer science metaphor then long-term
memory in a computer is hard drive it is
a a spacious and uh cheaper um you know
uh memory system
um working memory is more flexible
faster and more expensive and in
computers it's called Ram random exess
memory so uh moving
forward uh the long-term memory the hard
drive if you wish this is a very old
model that I think also Mark SS uses
quite a bit in his theories when he says
repress never returns he relies on this
chart quite a bit uh it was introduced
by Squire in 1992 who stated that you
know long-term memory can be divide it
into explicit or declarative memory and
implicit non- declarative
memory and if we open the working memory
uh you know component then this model
has been revised and there are some
Alternatives versions but one of the
current views is that it consists of
this
subsystems one of the simpler ones is
phological Loop where we uh simply uh
take in auditory information such as
musical sounds or speech it's not a huge
space it's about two or three UNS of
information and visual spatial sketchpad
where we process Visual and spatial
information Central executive is the
coordinator and you know it it allocates
attention this is the most resource
intensive uh component of the work in
memory the newer component that would is
introduced later is called episodic
buffer and this is not a monos sensory
space this is a multi-sensory space one
of the sort of mysteries was that
photological Loop is two or three units
and we can retain
so this is one of the reasons why ptic
buffer is introduced but uh it can be
used to binding things together between
senses such as you know Visual and
auditory data and importantly if you
look at that chart you can observe that
this binding can occur
without uh the deployment of expensive
Central executive system you can see
that their connections from visual to
the phological loop directly without the
deployment of expensive uh Central
executive
resources I've already used the term
binding and it simply refers to linking
the features into objects such as color
red and shape Square we quickly create
an object red square and then we stop
thinking about it in terms of processing
speech you know the two terms that uh
are pertinent to us is within sentence
binding and across sentence binding and
as the name suggests within sentence
binding refers to using our storage
language knowledge to apply to Temporary
retention of single sentences in a
relatively automatic manner without
using expensive you know attentional
resources and across sentence binding is
the same thing where we connect together
multiple
sentences um I will illustrate both
again on the example that I already gave
you uh on a cold winter day in 1964 a
jazz club Magnolia in Chicago caught on
fire the firefighters were on the scene
within 10 minutes
if we slow down here and see what's
happening when we hear this if I start
reading on a cold winter then if you're
familiar with American English you know
that the next word coming is day and
that's a prediction that is based on
your knowledge of language a semantic
prediction if you wish similarly towards
the end you can hear firefighters were
on the scene within 10 you know that the
next word coming is minutes I'm already
introducing the concept of redundancy in
speech sequential redundancy if you wish
and here was an example of a semantic
one and tactically because you know the
structure of affirmative sentence in
English after you hear the subject a Jaz
Club Magnolia you know that the verb is
coming and you're waiting for
it uh you will also Chunk on a cold
winter day together you will chunk Jaz
Club Magnolia together and within 10
minutes and of course you'll chunk
prepositions and articles together with
nouns in
1964 semantically is just one unit of
information not three different ones
phonetically in English it's four
syllables in Russian it's 12 so we we
save resources quite a bit if you wish
we're doing compression you know across
sentence binding uh uh is working uh but
only when the story is coherent and you
can see here in this example that the
two sentences are causally related there
is also a temporal structure where there
was the fire first and fire fire second
and there's a meaning you know when we
read the story or hear it with wondering
about whether the firefighters were in
the scene quickly enough and then you
you hear a confirmation of this
prediction that they were on the scene
quickly all of that helps us process the
information now we can fiddle with that
a little bit and introduce a meaningless
but syntactically correct sentence such
as the chsky example colorless green
ideas sleep furiously not very easy to
retain because we're trying to make
sense of it and it's not working and we
stay stay with it a while or here is a
meaningful but syntactically problematic
sentence this is a poem from uh an
Stevenson called Utah beside him the
gray-headed man has let one arm slide
awkwardly over his shoulder he's talking
and pointing at whatever it is so it's
not just the length of this phrase but
the way it's structured makes it
problematic for us to retain it so you
need both coherence and meaning if
however you're dealing with the very
first example of 10 words that are
unrelated that I gave you I'm not saying
it's impossible to bind them it is
possible but it will be more resource
demanding more expensive so to
speak these are formal definitions of
within sentence binding and across
sentence binding again the important
part is we do this relatively
automatically without additional costs
of expensive you know if you wish or
metabolically costly
resources uh under certain assumptions
you know and uh similarly we can do
cross- sentence binding but we have a
coherent and meaningful
story here is the kicker uh that you
know according to Daniel kanaman and we
can look at many other perspectives
including Mark SS in his book uh Hidden
Spring brain mind is an effective or
efficient or you could call it lazy
Processing Unit which means that we tend
to fall back to simplest possible
processing regime and we only deploy
complex processing when we have
to um
uh you in terms of emotions you know
there is an effect effect that a
company's effort which is strain with it
doesn't feel so good when we apply
effort and if you uh have a video camera
across from your face uh with a
relatively fast frame rate if you're
trying to do 17 * 69 in your mind you
will see that your pupil's dialate
unless you have iconic memory unless
you're Sant then for most people it
takes some effort and as a speculation
why is it that we have unpleasant effect
when we apply effort you know possibly
this is so because it is dangerous to
operate on nearly depleted resources for
more vulnerable and less resilient and
Conan's example is that if you are doing
17 * 69 in your head while trying to
make a left turn into traffic you're
more likely to run into an
accident so as a result if our activity
demands that we do complex processing
then it means conscious commitment to do
in complex processing in neuros
pychological terms that probably means
impulse inhibition we need to inhibit
the impulse to fall back to a simpler
regime and then we're PR well because
we're human to this Universal phenomenon
of fatigue any single functional task in
the brain mind that we do will get tired
such as impulse inhibition this is why
when people walk out of the gym they
sometimes eat a
donut um now it pertains to therapy very
very strongly you know we're tired on
Friday night you know compassion fatigue
auditory fatigue you know We crave
silence so what I'm trying to say is no
matter how trained the uh therapist is
no matter you know how experienced and
skilled none of us are superhuman beings
with unlimited work memory and we're all
prone to narrative fallacy at certain
times the two obstacles that I see on
the way of this discussion one is
simpler which is people being unaware of
the issue
and this is easier to correct when we
just talk about it but I've also faced
some denial while people fled out say
that this is a non issue and what are
you talking about and there is no
problem
here and this is why I think that the
primary effort of the paper was to kind
of bring awareness to this and to
discuss it I could be wrong but I'd like
to hear substantive arguments about
this another interesting you know
connection point before we move on to
clinical is the thought by Mark SS which
he voiced years ago I don't recall even
on which seminar it's about the fact
that how we think influences how we work
in a clinical
practice and this is a very broad term
this phras is sound so simple that it
may be even appearing trivial but it's
not well for example what we know and
what we don't know influences it if you
can imagine a clinician who happens to
be unaware that thyroid dysfunction may
present as an anxiety disorder or
depression then they will never ask this
question to their patient when was the
last time they sawed primary care doctor
and did thyroid penal blood
work um you know or some clinicians are
taught to not ask questions because
they're experiential and they derive
conclusions based on experience and then
they don't know and could be treating
Hashimoto disease and therapy you know
until cows come
home um you know personal therapy
changes how we think uh whether we can
think flexibly such as using categories
with discrete data dead or alive and
using continuous thinking with
continuous data such as temperature can
we even think statistically do we know
how to do that um can we think in terms
of Dynamics complexity and emergence or
we think mostly in deterministic and
static ways all of these things matter
and they influence how we
work so uh a related concept is a case
formulation and I wanted to mention that
this is not unique to psychotherapy that
uh it's used in medicine and L you know
experienced neurologist can start
suspecting Parkinson's before the
patient walks into the Consulting room
because he hears shuffling outside the
office right and then the patient walks
in and information is collected and you
see rigid you know maybe flat effect
effect rigid posture difficulty
initiating movement cognitive slowness
um and shuffling gate and rolling pin
Tremor and then the neurologist is in
client to say that I think that you
might have Parkinson's disorder
Parkinson's disease which is a
formulation this is a sentence this is a
story and the Gap explanatory Gap was
filled in from what the neurologist
knows from his
training and formally uh primary tool
you know this is the definition a case
formulation is a hypothesis about the
causes precipitant and maintaining
influences of person's psychological
interpersonal and behavioral problems
and you know I think personally that
it's one of the primary Tools in
conceptualizing what's going on with a
patient and it's very complex the little
vignettes that you'll hear uh in a few
minutes are
oversimplified shortened and a little
artificial you know it it usually takes
several sessions to come up with a
preliminary
formulation but to be very honest among
many other things a case formulation is
a story among other function
so here is a short case this is taken
from a paper by peran colleages in 2006
called psycho Dynamic formulation its
purpose structure and clinical
application Mr a is a 52-year-old
married businessman he presents on his
own initiative with a depressive
syndrome after being once again passed
over for promotion he himself does not
understand this rejection but it is
probably related to his lifelong
tendency to procrastinate and to annoy
his superiors either by being obsequious
or by challenging their Authority he has
a history of two untreated depressive
syndromes one in his 30s that also
followed a professional failure and one
in his 40s that followed his son's
defiant marriage to a woman of another
religion Mr A's father was was a sickly
professionally frustrated type
personality who died of a heart attack
when Mr a was in his scenes his mother
has always been a martyr with sming
despair characterized by chronic
insomnia self-doubt obsessive
ruminations and social withdraw she
never sought treatment Mr a has
essential hypertension for which he
takes aopa to 150 milligrams his
mother's history suggests a genetic
predisposition for a unipolar depression
let's imagine that this is all the
information that we
have now let's take this to a
psychologist just a psychodynamic
clinician who was trained in the
tradition of ego psychology it goes back
to Sigman Freud was elaborated by Hanna
Freud Charles brener and others and this
is a formulation uh I want to point out
that in each of those examples you will
hear a highlight and Mark SS does this
you'll hear the central theme the main
point so in egos psychology you may hear
something like this Mr A's central
conflict is between an unconscious wish
to kill off his competitors and an
unconscious fear that he will be killed
if he acts on that wish whenever he
expresses derivations of his competitive
wish directly he becomes frightened of
retaliation he therefore resorts to
expressing the wish indirectly by
passive aggressive Maneuvers such as
procrastination conversely whenever he
responds to this fear of retaliation by
being solicitous and obedient he
inwardly feels resentful and diminished
to contain the struggle Mr a has
developed intellectual mechanisms that
although adaptive for certain aspects of
his work Mal adaptive interpersonally
and that they isolate him emotionally
from others I apologize to you know you
know his team psychoanalysts on the
panel but you know for for the audience
I just want to highlight that in egos
psychology you will hear conflict you
know uh a formulation will contain
conflict typically between a wish and a
fear but that's is sort of uh the
style let's look at the same exact
patient from the psy self- psychological
standpoint that goes back to heines Coho
and was elaborated by ghetto and others
mrr's Central problem consists of his
low self-esteem and consequent need for
continual recognition and approval from
others along with his inability to
accept any limitations either in himself
which led to disapproval from others or
in others which reduce the value of
their approval when it occurs presumably
during childhood his depressive mother
and sickly father
were so self-absorbed with their
problems that they were unable to
respond empathically to his age
appropriate aspirations at the same time
both parents narcissistically invested
in their son the hopes that his
achievement would make up for their
failures in self psychology you
typically hear about narcissistic
vulnerability difficulty idealizing
parent difficulty in mirroring uh
empathic Attunement and perhaps
narcissistic
extension
here's a third version this is object
relation school going back to melan
Klein Mr L's Central problem is the
failure to integrate the good and the
bad representations of himself and
others during childhood his depressed
mother could not respond to her son's
needs and demands Mr a is unconsciously
frightened that his resultant rage would
destroy the very one on whom he depended
he repressed his bad angry self and
acted like a good Obed and Son the
splitting was reinforced by interactions
with a controlling father who punitively
viewed any of Mr A's independent
assertions as acts of defiance in object
relations you will hear typically about
splitting or lack of
integration I want to say that you hear
some terminology and I don't want to
caricature it each of those formulations
is complex nuanced and indeed useful you
could get to good results in each of
those directions of the work but they
are very different and all I'm trying to
say is you can observe ve that they are
influenced by how people were taught and
what they
studied I want to ask you just to
reflect together do these formulations
seem uh elaborated and detailed or brief
and tenative how certain do you think
the author of each narrative is even if
they use euphemisms like it seems that
it appears that do they sound you know
uncertain okay in their
hypothesis this is a CBT example
uh from an authoritative Source CB
stands for cognitive behavioral therapy
this is American Psychological
Association essential components of CBT
for depression so nearly textbook
different patient but also depression I
suggested to Nancy that I spent a few
minutes in the session giving her a
first notion about how CBT would address
her difficulties to help her decide
whether she wanted to pursue it she
agreed to teach the cognitive model I
mapped on to a thought record the
situation Nancy described to me earlier
when her roommate Connie looked hurt
when Nancy turned down con's invitation
to go out to dinner I asked Nancy a
short series of Socratic questions to
show her how these thoughts made her
feel guilty inadequate and trapped so in
a CBT example this is more cognitive
therapy than behavioral you see that the
thoughts are being analyzed and are put
into position of kind of causes that the
patterns of her thoughts are causing the
symptoms you had conflict in ego psych
you had you know uh narcissistic
vulnerability and lack of idealization
of the self psych you had splitting here
we have thoughts Here's the final
perspective and quite oversimplified and
artificial but at the same time while
you and I you know we all talking here
you there's many psychiatrists in the
world who diagnose their patients with
major depressive disorder and prescribe
as as
arise uh here is the story of chemical
and balance this is chemical imbalance
in their minds leading to the
symptoms this is based on a story called
a monoamine theory of
depression and these you know clinicians
who are thoughtful and and you know
trained in well meaning they've read
many peer-reviewed studies with some
statistical results of ssris we now know
that the uh uh the effect is uh weak
that it's 3 effect size compared to 0. n
of dynamic therapy for depression but
nonetheless there's modest effect the
important part is that no psychiatrist
will be able to explain to you the
causal chain of events from a molecular
level of Serotonin all the way to the
macro phenomenon of depression that is
transient you know emergent and you know
um complex and
dynamic uh so then the connection from
molecular level of Serotonin to the to
the symptoms was made exclusively
through the clinicians Theory and
nothing else and this this is an example
of also narrative
fallacy um I want to also say a few
words there's more of that in the paper
about verifiability so once the
preliminary hypothesis are formed the
question is can we truly test them and
if you remember the texts from each
School of psychoanalysis then I say that
they're not specific enough and not
falsifiable enough if you take the you
know scientific statement that is
falsifiable such as water boils under
normal pressure at 100° Centigrade it
would take a single observation to
disprove it you you can observe water
under normal pressure boiling at 90
degrees and you're done but none of the
statements you heard before are
falsifiable in that
way and also many were really
nonspecific now even if psychiatrist
let's say uses response to medication as
data you know uh if if you're saying
something like I gave somebody Rin and
they're better therefore they have a HD
this is is flawed because if you give a
stimulant to anybody they will attend
better and therefore it doesn't prove
that a person has ADHD this is an
example of circular
logic another uh obstacle on our path is
Barnum effect and forer effect it's the
same thing but I think that people don't
talk about it enough essentially what it
means is if you feel resonance with a
certain idea or paragraph or a patient
feels resonance that says absolutely
nothing about how clinically useful it
is is accurate and and uh none of that
here's an illustration of what actually
for did he gave his students personality
questionnaire and inventory they
answered it honestly and then he mailed
them results which were identical to one
another and he took these results from
an astrology book subsequently he asked
them to rate how uh they compared these
text to how they felt about themselves
how accurate they you know they thought
it was on a one to five scale and they
rated it as 4 something I think
4.5 now astrologist milk that effect
like there's no tomorrow this is their
livelihood there's a way to present a
text with certain things in it like
detail um it has to be detailed and then
when you read it something will resonate
but it absolutely doesn't mean that it's
accurate the third bullet is effort
justification bias and I think that the
hypothesis you heard before you know
they took a bit of work to formulate and
a bit of thinking which is effort and it
is not that easy to let go of something
that you developed with effort and
finally some clinicians use what's
called response to intervention to uh
decide to gauge if they're on the right
track for example if you deliver an
interpretation and the patient cries you
tend to think that you're accurate and I
think it's a very error Pro method so
that if somebody punches me in the face
and I cry it doesn't mean that the
intervention was therapeutic it could be
iatrogenic and there's many more details
on that in the paper but to summarize I
think that sadly we do not have a
rigorous independently verifiable
framework of hypothesis testing we we
think that we do we declare that we're
hypothetically deductive but I think if
we go down to it it it is
not um moving on to active inference
perspective and I apologize to you know
analysts who are um you know not not
close to this framework or any anyone in
the audience but the idea that I shared
before that brain mind tends to resort
to simpler regimes of processing and
only deploys complexity when absolutely
necessary is not news to active
inference Community this is a formula
for variational free energy and you see
that it can be decomposed as complexity
minus
accuracy so if you minimize variational
free energy then complexity is minimized
and this is the principle of a coms
Razer where you are seeking an accurate
explanation but among several you will
pick the one that is
simplest
um there is certainly the word inference
and belief is is completely koshering
good in active inference community and
this is a big part of the model however
all inferences are probabilistic they're
statistical and they're quantitatively
verified
and I don't think none of the hypothesis
I showed before are probabilistic and
quantitatively
verified there's a viewpoint on
emotional inferences in active inference
community and from that perspective you
could say that anxiety is just a
commitment to a basian belief that I am
anxious which best explains the
prevailing sensory in interceptive
cues finally you can look at the some of
the processes happening in Psychotherapy
from the active inference standpoint
perhaps before the patient and therapist
meet therapist has certain generative
models uh we learn how shame is
different from guilt how acute fear is
different from anxiety there's different
kinds of anxiety and then we meet a
patient and we have to adjust our models
based on the specific information coming
at us which is again perception and
adjustment of the models at some point
we could infer if we're feeling
something in therapy say counter
transference what is it that I'm feeling
that's an inference or what is it that
the patient is feeling and then we could
act even silently if we label it in our
minds that I'm feeling fear right now
without saying it out loud that's an
action mental action and so this
framework of model and for Act is is
fits very well in the active inference
framework uh the take-home message I
think if we look at narrative fallacy is
that when we are driven by Theory more
so than by the patient's data then we
tend to perceive less and act more we're
modifying the environment based on
overly confident beliefs and such as the
example of a CBT clinician teaching the
patient you know they're teaching the
patient right issue another issue is
that a very high level of precision High
certainty in internal beliefs and that
violates the principle of Maximum
enthropy by James which is cited by Carl
friston what this States is that
internal beliefs have Brad entropy by
entropy the entropy is minimized but the
entropy of beliefs is
maximized the next issue is that okay
when we have data coming to us that
either confirms our predictions or
disconfirms them we know what to do but
if there's no data coming in when
there's you know uh uncertainty it is uh
uh important to not act um which
corresponds to Freud's principle of
abstinence until we have enough data to
say something or to correct the beliefs
so and just to summarize in my opinion
and I'll be happy to be corrected the
formulations above and in the peerreview
paper are not high entropy they're
confident they're elaborated they
contain conclusions based upon
conclusions while the whole thing was
based on
assumptions so we can declare and state
that we're not attached to the theory
but I don't know if that is so in
clinical practice what else do we have
after all to fill in the Gap
um so I think we can try to conclude
that it is important to stay datadriven
more so than Theory driven that we need
to be trying to test our inferences in
the environment to the degree possible
and for that they need to be formulated
in a falsifiable way it's important to
remember that inferences are
probabilistic which requires and
necessitates the ability to think
statistically and not only in the story
form also want to say that what happens
when there is you know uh one school of
thought or identification I I quite
often hear from very experienced coins I
am a clian analyst or I am an EMDR
therapist or I use effective
Neuroscience to infer what is the main
emotional problem for the patient so in
these uh circumstances I think the
chance of narrative fallacy is higher
because we are operating within this one
school now if we're able to take
multiple viewpoints and stay in Merit to
all of them there you know that that
would decrease the probability because
sometimes we can use you know Amman
perspective and Tomkins and talk about
shame being Central in narcissis this is
not what you're going to hear if you're
studying neuros pycho analysis and
clinical Workshop you will hear about
the play System
right uh we don't talk about shame
enough uh so I think awareness about
narrative fallacy and Barnum effect
allows us to resist the temptation of
confusing coherent and meaningful as
clinically accurate and useful
coherent and meaningful texts and
psychon analytic language are
seductive um so I hope to have an sort
of discussion about narrative fallacy I
think that if we connect the dots by
using the glue of the theory duure and
nothing else it's a problem I think that
we can consider updating how we do case
formulations and move away from
exclusively story driven form you can
already find it in uh Mam's latest book
uh psycho analytic supervision she uses
10 dimensional assessment some variables
are continuous some are uh uh discreet
but you know I think that you know it
moves away from the story form in some
domains of
learning and uh I think also talking
honestly about possibility of using
Tools in our work in addition to
narratives is important like
neurologists talk to the patient and
they examine the patient but they have
MRI Pat scan
EG and uh these are completely different
ways of analysis than talking to a
patient and I certainly think that we
can teach these things uh
differently um wanted to share that so
far I haven't heard any push back from
CBT or psychiatrists CBT colleagues or
psychiatrists but some of my
psychoanalytic colleagues and
psychodynamic colleagues uh
expressed uh push back it and I
classified it in four different the mes
the first one is the most frequent thing
you hear from psycho analysis you
painted a straw man the second one is
that I Alexi am not a psychoanalyst and
I have not read enough Freud Lan Klein
Coho Etc uh some people say that psycho
analysis is Art and not science also
quite frequently I hear I don't work
this way which in some cases took a form
of I don't formulate cases and I
struggle with that actually because if
we do clinical work and our patients
have some probability of a complete
suicide I wonder if this clinician
honestly doesn't think if they only in
it and feel things right some people say
this is an American thing what you're
talking about we don't do it in our
country we work with a transference
psychon analytic field Theory keris and
I fled out her you know there is no
fallacy so I think that these are
defensive reactions I am not sure why
because I'm saying it applies generally
not only to Dynamic work but to CBT and
Psychiatry but also to Jal as T pointed
out to
economics and I'm hopeful to maybe have
a discussion about it and uh we are
right here so we can discuss um thank
you great thank you all right let us go
to any of our panel in in order who can
say hello and give any first remarks and
we'll just kind of go around and from
there if there's any chance to start
with Andrea I would be most grateful he
wrote A Commentary in the chat great
I'll I'll read the the comment in the
chat Andrea wrote Alexi very interesting
and sorry I have to leave but I'm sure
you will discuss on the major role of
aexs in the memorization and in The
Binding of the different components in
the anxiety-provoking story of the Jazz
Club fire as compared to the list to
memorize whereas the affect of coloring
is completely
absent could you say more about
that yes I think Andrea is uh bringing
up uh it sound working okay
yeah is bringing up an important part I
think Christina alberini and others talk
about it when there is a effective tone
in the messages we we uh tend to retain
information stronger and better uh so
that if fire evokes fear or anxiety in
somebody it will be a stronger memory
and certainly what I what I've mentioned
are very simplistic ways of looking at
things but I think when emotions are
present when we memorize things uh
here's a mark s's example you know when
children do two thinkers in power outlet
single exposure lifetime memory intense
effect pain you know doesn't take any
repetition single exposure memory for
Life phobic memory so I I think that
perhaps I overlooked this important part
but yeah um I I uh I think it is uh
important to mention and to add to this
to this
discussion go ahead and unmute David and
then go for
it oh unmute David and then go for
it
okay uh
so on the affect uh aspect of
narrative um seems to
me
that's that I listen
to
whatever I hear from the perspective of
a
integrative
uh unitary
self
and that self is conscious and
unconscious but and but it's an act of
my
brain and it it seems to me that
narratives have to include all the
components of
Consciousness in
them and that so I would like to talk
more about about the
issue of the why you know you talk to us
Alexy in a narrative way and we respond
in that way
and uh there's no way to eliminate it um
I I think the easy part of your
discussion it's the second
point is dealing with case formulation
um uh which I think you would agree with
but my position is the case formulations
are good for
communication with yourself or with
others uh but are
not that are they're contradictory to
listening and proper the ideal level of
involvement
and you know it's great to learn all
those stories and have them in the back
of your head and but not to be thinking
about
them uh because they get in the way of
your
responsiveness and your ability to
listen properly and I feel like you know
I've been at this now for 45 years and
the
I it's like a comfortable chair that I
just sit down and um attune myself to
whatever it is that is my way of
analytic
listening and and and participating
and I I might think about a particular
patient maybe if it strikes me me as uh
self psychology
descriptor uh or something like that but
I think the case
formulations get in the way of actively
doing
Psychotherapy would you like me to
respond or sure
please uh you've said many useful things
David and uh I think that um
um we may not formulate and listen to
the patient at exactly the same
millisecond uh but you know I think
usually I'm quoting Marx Holmes again
when people show up in dynamic therapy
or psycholytic
therapy this is uh a referral request
that contains an explanatory Gap when
the patient walks in and says I'm afraid
of elevators I don't want to write an
elevator don't even worry about my mom
and dad and whatever this is a very
concrete form and they don't need
dynamic therapy they can do exposure
when they have OCD and they want to walk
out the house you know they need
exposure when people come in and they
say I feel badly but I don't know what
it is and how it is or I'm doing
something I know I shouldn't be doing it
but I'm doing it anyway so and part of
the work of course we listen for a long
time for as long as it takes we'll think
together with a patient and come up with
some
hypothesis about what this is and uh I
think it's inevitable I mean if we bring
clinical work so 25% of mental health
professionals experience a completed
suicide of a patient in our careers if
we're dealing with somebody who has
acute PTSD this is not like speculation
but they've been tortured and they have
flashbacks and Nightmares in the whole
nine years probability of a completed
suicide is five times higher so I must
think I have to think at least to do
risk anal Paris do they need
hospitalization right now or other
things and I think that our minds are
never fully blank when we're listen I
think that's an illusion from be Hest
like you know no memory No Agenda it's
good to declare that but our minds are
not blank when we're listen and we think
while listening so this is all like
intertwin
so so I agree my mind is not blank is
I'm just not
aware of How It's
tuned to I'm doing it's like an
instrument and I agree with you that at
various moments in the work with
patients we need to have explanations to
things and then a formulation can be of
use in some way uh I'm not talking about
in psychoanalytic language
but the at the level of description or
communication it when those moments
occur in
therapy then some formulation is needed
and but I'm talking about the
psychoanalytic schools of thought as
describing a patient in a
formulation is good to have the
knowledge for all the different
schools and to find you find your own
way of listening to the
patient certainly uh I I just wanted to
also say that we're not only listening
you know at some point I mean if we were
just listening then patient can talk to
a wall right you know some point we do
things such as clarification
confrontation interpretation you know
containment and these things all of them
should be driven by working
understanding of what's going on if
we've got no formulation in our heads we
have no compass on how to act in therapy
even if listen for I didn't say it's not
in my head sure I'm not conscious of it
right right right yeah yeah but I think
I've said enough and I think David and I
will mostly agree on many different
things yeah but U thank you maybe
yeah um anyone else has any comments or
questions critique
anything um sh sh shall I uh time in
there okay um well first off thank you
for having me
um I prepared some comments um I'm
afraid Alexa you will classify me in the
defensive people I I'll try to seduce
you not to do so but we'll
see um so um Alexa of course you are
more than right when you warn for the
problem uh page 11 of hyper serans where
we draw connections between the pieces
of data without any reason other than
our Theory driven
beliefs or I would say more generally
when we understand uh between quotes uh
the problem of our
patient you know I'm linan so Jac laon
famously warned in the same vein the
clinicians or maybe everybody beware of
understanding that's what he said Beware
of
understanding so I do profoundly not
think that clinical work is about
understanding at least not at his
conscious cognitive semantic level and I
also agree that the monoamine theory of
depression has the same logical status
from that standpoint as the discussion
of a state of panic from the standpoint
of udle Dynamics on page
24 and I will try to show how one can do
clinical work without making
interpretations not sure if that's going
to hold um
so not to take too much time I had
prepared um a paragraph about the
importance of
transference so I'm just going to name
that uh
paragraph um I'm sure you're aware of
this importance but you just said
something to David that everything that
we do as clinicians in our th in our
therapeutic session uh should be driven
by hypothesis about the patient and I do
think
that whoever is the
patient um there are some like Universal
principles uh to work with patients and
one of them is um to be
unconditional uh and so many of the
actions taken in therapy from the
clinician is actually driven by this
principle of being
unconditional and other principles in
the same ve
which are some sometimes called the
Solon principles presence proximity
patience
availability these kind of
things so I I really do think
that
establishing a transference relationship
and I I wouldn't think about TR
transference and counter transference
we're both in there although the
relationship is not
symmetrical um is um
establishing uh an an apparatus which
will work or might work uh for therapy
and that many of the actions of the
therapist um are uh aimed at uh
establishing this
apparatus so my third paragraph is of
course that there is more to the
clinical work than the transference
relationship uh you could say the
transference relationship is how the
therapist engages in a therapy with his
subjective um
apparatus um but there is also the
intellectual investment of the
clinician and to me that is not about
interpretation at least not
interpretation as is given on page 12
about the ego weaknesses
Etc in Dutch that is the language which
in which I first did clinical work there
are actually two words there is
interpretation and ding which resonates
with the German
Dum like in the Trum Trum
Dum interpretation is an addition of
content while Dum is a form of pointing
underscoring
punctuation so I have prepare the slide
uh to show what I mean um I'm not sure I
can I will try
to
um um
yeah thank
you
um see what that
gives
um let me
see I can do like that is that fine too
yep that's fine thank you I'll prop it
so it's visible so three little cases um
in in
which maybe it's EU instead of UE I have
a doubt now has given effects um maybe
these are effects that you would qualify
as fallacy but let me explain
so early on in my practice I had a
patient who had uh troubles uh with uh
anxious obsessions whenever she got
anxious she started to count one 2 three
Etc and she also would have specific
rituals which involved a bed and
especially which involved um drinking
cups and she would with her finger go
around the drinking cup from left to
right and from right to left and count
and go around the handle from left from
down to uh from up to down from down to
up and
count
and it just the order that struck me
because in Dutch the word for um a
drinking cup is the same word as for
head
and the word for the handle is the same
word as for
ear so my patient was talking about in
Dutch that
cop and I only said that
betop she let me say that she told her
story and I pick picked up these words
that these are words that she said and I
only picked up these words and I put
them in a sequence bet cop or because it
struck me and this was enough this was
enough it
was early on in my practice and quite
spectacular to open up like you would
have cut somewhere where suddenly
everything comes out of
it where there started a chain of
associations in which she then recounted
how as a little kid she had anesthesia
and the anesthesia was done at the level
of her head and at the level of her ear
and that she was extremely anxious that
she would not wake up and that she had
learned to soothe herself by counting so
that she would count until she went to
sleep and that she would as soon as she
wake up take up the count again as a
kind of way to make a
a chain um a tread that kept her
alive so this was spectacular because
the whole session was one Association
after the other about
these Hospital
experiences and about other connections
he was making and it the the the session
was not enough to contain her uh she
came home and she wrote an email I got
an email with uh other associations and
uh and at the new session she started
over again
so yeah at least you could say this uh
made the patient move the patient moved
she she moved
mentally um so that was something let's
say it was
something in another case um my patient
another patient
um uh spoke about her life and her
difficulties and also about her
childhood and her upbringing and she was
brought up in a religious community and
they had rituals and prayers and one of
these prayers said uh it was one of the
prayers she had she had kept in memory
uh Jesus in the middle so this in Dutch
is said Jesus in the middle
so what I only said is I only fragmented
it differently I said youus ADM and that
changed the meaning from Jus in the mid
from Jesus in the middle to your sister
in the middle so
again this sparked associations and um
uh associations about her compet
competitive feelings towards her sister
and a mental movement
the third example is an example not of
my practice but it's been published by a
psychoanalyst and thean psychoanalyst
his name is Patrick guier
lafi and he speaks about a middle-aged
patient um who who who comes to his
practice and uh says to him I'm almost
ashamed to come and ask for your time
and attention because everything goes
quite well in my life I have a happy
marriage I have a happy happy job I have
good children but it so happens that now
and then seemingly from nowhere I have
these heavy moods and these depressions
and I don't know how it
comes so she counts her story like all
the patients do and at one point she
says in some kind of context where she
speaks about her
mother my my mother couldn't in in in in
French uh
my but instead of
saying she
says she has a little pose on an an
awkward moment in the sentence she
says so normally you would say in
French and she says
and the analyst who is hears this and
this is awkward this is not why you
would the way you would speak this
sentence and he said the only thing he
does is he repeats
that and then she hears what she said
because this changes the
sentence the
pap it misses it's missing in my slide
it's the the key
means uh daddy came
back and so when she hears what she said
daddy came back she suddenly starts to
cry she had already counted the story of
her father leaving her and her mother uh
when she was young and her mother being
alone to raise her um and and she being
very loyal um with her to her mother
but now that she hears P comes back she
realizes that she actually had longed
for the for her father coming back but
that is longing she couldn't let go of
it or she couldn't express it because
that would be like not being loyal to
her mother who was alone and who was um
Angry towards her husband having left
her and she felt it a duty to be on the
mother's side
but uh being at her mother's size she
she couldn't um uh um process her
longing of her father coming back and uh
her sadness about his absence she
couldn't process that because there was
no place for that and now in the
analysis she she could do
that uh I see your hands is Raising and
I know I'm been talking already a lot
but these are three examples in which
mental movement is induced without
adding semantic uh material it's it's
about it's about doting about pointing
to something so I had two Auto
paragraphs three Auto paragraphs but one
small uh so but I first uh leave you
uh you you raised your hand so I guess
you want to say
something Alex if that if that's okay
with everybody
yeah yeah so Arian I I think that I want
to separate two things one is I honestly
admire your work I say it absolutely
sincerely without flattery that these
are creative interventions and I love
hearing Vates like this I've had similar
moments where I went to a visual
metaphor and it opened up the work uh I
think you a fantastic uh uh clinician
and analyst and your patients are very
fortunate to be in your care uh I that's
that's why statement that I honestly
mean the second statement is I don't
know if we can use these vignettes to uh
generalize I don't know actually well
first of all when you says the patient
had anxious obsessions and rituals you
are already formulating these are
beginnings of a formulation you
classified her behavior as a ritual not
as a tick you know and so you've thought
about it okay but then when you said
something about these you know phrases
in a certain order or not and the
patient reacted by opening up and you
know recording the memory in the
hospital what we don't know Aran is
whether it was your words or your
nonverbals or the six months of analysis
that happened before then and the
containment that you created in a
relationship I don't really have grounds
for a causal inference that it's exactly
that interpretation that caused the
effect and finally I think that if we
look at case studies this is absolutely
powerful material but certainly not
grounds for uh causal statements because
again all clinical reports are
correlational data and I think I've used
that example with you from research book
by kin that if I you know um claim that
watching television for a week cures
common cold I could have 30 years of
experiments I could have tens of
thousands of patients each one of them
with a proper common C you know shows up
watches television for a week comes out
there's no common cult therefore
television cures common cult we don't
have data for causal statements we don't
know what exactly helped and
specifically whether interpretations or
not interpretations we have a school in
an in in the US called new school of
psychoanalysis with spots and they flat
out say interpretations don't work we
don't interpret they also say that their
field of psychoanalysis works for
schizophrenia but there is zero research
about their specific School of
psychoanalysis versus relations versus
lcan versus istdp nobody has done that
study we have General Studies on Dynamic
treatment but what style of dynamic
treatment in a randomized clinical trial
was never done so the the I think the
scientific answer is we don't know
exactly what worked and finally I think
if we're talking about Improvement of a
patient with you know anxious obsessions
and rituals and another thing the the
the good thing is um followup so if we
wait months after the work is done and
we collect thousand patients and we know
that the results stay for these thousand
patients then we have something to say
about the efficacy of this particular
modality of treatment if we don't have
followup in the session they go up they
go down they progress they regress so I
don't know if we can have grounds to
talk about you know clinical
improvements that's sort of my take and
again to go back in terms of how you
work you presented very sophisticated
vignettes and this is this is beautiful
among other things but I I just don't
know if it applies directly
right so I'm not I'm not sure of the
format of this because of course I could
reply on each point and I would like to
reply but um maybe the moderator can
come in
here it can be however you see it
definitely plant seeds to be explored
but how about Albert first give a Rel or
a totally different perspective and let
you see where we're at in a few minutes
well I would say first of all thank you
very much Alexi for the excellent paper
um and for the Pres presentation I'm
really loving the discussion so far as
well um I had some questions prepared as
well but most of them have already been
addressed
uh uh by all by you and the panel so
it's kind of like I'm thinking of
something significant I can say I think
I'm really curious about the discussion
between Aran and you right now so but
one thing I was curious about is in the
what we can do section of your paper um
and this is something you also mentioned
during your um during your speech is uh
well besides the audio verbal exchange
between the patient and therapist we can
use like additional tools and I was I
was um curious about like the objective
status of those tools and the data you
you acquire from these
tools cuz I'm guessing you also have to
integrate those into like a narrative so
what does that mean about uh yeah what
what does that say that's one thing and
secondly like how do you um how can you
present that to the patient and this
something you you you comment on in the
third point of the last part it's it's
it's about like some kinds of types of
therapy like betous BB they film their
patients and the baby and GDP does this
thing as well
but it it's I'm curious about have you
thought about like how would you
integrate these kinds of data but by all
means I'm I'm very curious on on your
comments as well so
yeah perhaps I can respond briefly and
uh you know this is a controversial
topic that evokes much debate but if we
go back to neurologist right let's say
the neurologist hears a patient case
where the patient is on unable to kind
of cross the street properly and they
have profound spatial deficits and they
they are sort of struggling from that
problem they cannot do mathematics okay
so they don't know exactly what's going
on they examine the patient ask them to
walk back and forth they talk to the
patient they may even order a neuros
psychological assessment but then they
order an imaging test such as an MRI and
they detect that there's a lemon size
you know leion in the right
hemisphere this is not a conversation
this is a different uh data point and
then they know theology they know what's
up that the spatial deficit was related
to this lesion in the right hemisphere
we don't do anything like that in
Dynamic treatment not at all we insist
that speaking to the patient listening
to the patient is it it's enough okay in
fact if you are talking about video
cameras you know in in some modalities
of dynamic treatment such as istdp
that's a standard practice they insist
and kind of it's you know you sign the
releases and everything but video
cameras are used or supervision and
learning I think in psycho analysis
proper that is considered kind of
anathema because you know first of all
it's intrusive there's a third in the in
the room which is a camera and that it
sort of privacy concerns and then you
know it distorts the transference
Dynamics and everything but you know
what then you're left with is words and
also nonverbals like the tone of voice
or the posture of the patient but we're
missing a lot by processing the data
coming at us through the work in memory
that is quite limited so uh just as an
example again batric bb beatric bb works
with uh infant mother diet where there
is no language at all you know there is
nonverbal exchange and dance baby's
doing gooo and mama is doing gaga and
sort
of uh because it is so
fast then they do a video and then they
slow play the video with Mom together
and they see the level of Attunement the
speed if you wish if the baby did this
and the mom didn't react or the baby
didn't do anything and the mom reacted
and you can talk about atunement or
misattunement in that play between a
baby and a mom beatric BB is a
psychoanalyst this is a completely
different data point different work from
words exchanged and thinking in words uh
because words are deterministic tools
they're not flows and they are
relatively they're averaged out and I
think that you know just at least
thinking opening the conversation about
using these additional data points in
addition to the narrative from the
patient and our feelings and inference
about their feelings would possibly
allow us you know to work with the
phenomenon here that is chaotic Dynamic
emergent
complex we we base so much on the words
and I think that's a very limited uh
data data set uh I don't know if that
answers your question
Albert uh yeah sure definitely but also
what about like the the question the
patient asks
for some questions are really comp
complex and are very difficult to
measure using that kind of data like for
example a patient comes to the clinic
and says um I lack meaning in my life
how do you measure that kind of stuff
well I I don't mean to trivialize things
that I'm going to do an MRI if they like
meaning in their life certainly we will
talk to them just like neurologist talk
to
but you know sometimes uh I hear about
the lack of meaning when the patient is
in a depressed state because when the
seeking system is down regulated there
is no hope there is no uh you know um
enthusiasm but also it's drained of
meaning the functional system of
salience network you know assigns
meaning to things that are have you know
uh uh values for us and and
downregulates other a dog in the field
will have value for uh a bone and value
for a female dog but no value for oak
tree right now uh this is I'm sorry
reductionistic example but I do think
that in addition to a global
philosophical high level discussion
what's the meaning of my life there is
you know other components of this
question of how does a patient talk
about meaning and and you could use
additional data points about that for
example when they are depressed they
will tell you the their life is
meaningless and you can discuss that
this is a phase of their life by the way
not a disease of major depression but a
mental state so um does that does that
answer yeah thank you thank
you
um
can you hear
me okay I really think that the language
Theory uh that is um that is used here
is extremely naive for example on page
11 um you say Alexi the world apple is
meaningless to a baby who never saw or
touched an apple this is this is to me
not really informed I mean even not
going into
psychoanalysis of course an apple can be
very meaningful even when it is not seen
or touched it is when when the when the
surroundings when a modern father speak
about the
Apple uh it becomes meaningful child
will hear it will will filter out the
world and word and will try to make
sense of it with with the context so
um you you could say indeed for example
that um this is all coincidence Etc
but there there are several things um of
course I I give you here three examples
now there are thousands of these
examples this is not just three examples
I mean this is empirical stuff that
clinicians here in their very very
privileged position of listening to the
intimacy of the patient we have a
possibility of observing what no one
else can
observe and this empirical stuff uh um
we should do honor to it we should we
should do uh as we are in let's we have
like a microscope that nobody else has
um from right when he first encountered
these um uh
ambiguity um uh Elements which are
clinically meaningful of course he said
like this is nonsense but it is not
because it is nonsense that uh and it
goes against all the theories that it
does not exist like uh shakko used to
say it is because Darwin was really
really uh drawing everything he saw with
ultimate Precision that and he gathered
data and he gathered a lot of data that
he made up a theory the theory uh had
only a chance to exist it's the only
chance that it exist because you are
drawing reality Point by point so your
data driven model I couldn't agree more
you have this this is the chance where
the data the clinical data have a chance
of existing
and and this is the way science work you
make a theory Darwin made a theory that
went against all rational all uh evident
um um um understanding of the world at
that point and Freud speaks about the
the primary process and he says this is
something we we find ridicule and we
scorn and we laugh about it but still it
is there and so he
he made a theory Darwin based upon all
kind of data which he gathered and then
he he he had the um the courage to make
his theory this theory that he made
which was not yet proven
allowed um experimental
researchers first of one which was
mendal to uh device and think of such an
experimental uh um uh setup that could
uh falsify his
theory this experimental setups could
not be thought without this Theory they
needed that theory to make up that
experiment so it is a Pity that of
course generations of clinicians do not
like experimental research but if I I
can uh share again my
screen uh I do think that there is a big
future for experimental
psychoanalysis and uh this is ex this uh
uh precisely what I'm doing and um we
are finding measures to falsify falsify
test uh the is there any chance I could
finish just one more minute this is the
geocat and shows predominant primary
processing in acute psychosis and in uh
psychic transparency this is a
laboratory induced uh setup to induce
parapraxis and it shows that parapraxis
are defensively motivated and this is uh
another um uh uh publication about the
ability of people solving weebus without
knowing it which is one of the uh
elements that we should um um uh suppose
if people have this clinical um uh this
clinical uh
manifestations so um uh at least at the
very least even if you can kind of
relativize and and and draw uh put away
all these these these elements as
coincidence at the very least as a
scientific honesty we should take this
hypothesis seriously and test it that is
scientifically honest
so I did not mean to interrupt you it's
just my work in memory buffer was
getting full from the previous episode
so when you moved to slides I started
getting packet drops and I forgot to I'm
writing things down but I wanted to
because you said something very
important before I want to go back to
first of all you've made a comment about
the apple and I'm sorry if it sounds
uninformed I happen to be a father and
and so I've experienced you know uh
fatherhood and uh I want to be specific
about what I mean before we criticize it
is you know babies from birth have
reflexes they have rooting reflex they
have orienting reflex and other things
now when when baby had doesn't have you
know visual system developed enough to
perceive an apple it is certainly
meaningless because she can't like it
can detect sweet versus sour and it can
Orient uh but it doesn't you know then
there is no apple because you can't
detect it and then when it sees
something Apple versus a cup you know if
if I what's stated in the paper is the
word Apple okay the word apple is a
bunch of sounds to a baby that doesn't
understand the meaning it cannot decode
it it may hear Mommy and Daddy say that
but also mommy and daddy using million
other words and all I'm saying is when
we say meaning that means you can decode
you can say what it means and there's
some chain of associations and other
than Mommy or Daddy using the word Apple
once I I don't think you have much but
when the baby bites an apple and
experiences you know through experience
The Taste and the Crunch and then the
the word apple is associated with
tactile gustatory you know all Factory
experiences then you have another ball
game and certainly there is no bright
line but I meant that you need to have
long-term memory to make sense of the
world that's all it means just to be
specific another thing is I certainly
don't say let's throw away all the
theories absolutely that's not the point
as Kurt Levan said a good theory is the
most practical thing you can have uh
that being said I want to be precise
about theories and specific so and uh
for example uh when people use the term
iology such as a certain word like black
beetle was eological and panic okay
iology means
causal I don't think there's any grounds
to say that the word black beetle is
causal for a panic attack panic attack
is a complex multiply determined
phenomenon that is related to bed
nucleus ofri analis anterior singular
cortex you know perhaps it may have some
triggers you know but it's a complex
phenomenon that should not be reduced to
being triggered by a certain word in in
panic disorder and if we look at
clinical things the definition of a
panic attack is that it comes unexpected
there is no trigger if it is triggered
then technically we're not talking about
a panic disorder so I'm just saying that
you know in order for us to test
something it needs to be falsifiable
otherwise we're we're we can cannot test
a statement you can certainly test
falsifiable I've been tested and and
I've published it well all I'm saying is
as part of your work you know so when
you have work with 1,400 students and
you've conducted the um the uh French
par um uh rebuses the the complex tasks
I think what you've proven with your
research is that people can can
unconsciously solve the Rebus and that
is valuable addition to other work which
mark ssite with uh uh takoscope where we
can unconsciously read simple things we
can count simple things we can associate
face with a word
unconsciously that's all it means but it
doesn't prove that Lan is correct in
saying that unconscious structured as a
language that is not a falsifiable
statement that unconscious is structured
as a language that's a belief yeah you
can put it in in different parts and and
and test different parts is the first
part of it is important because it's
never supposed it's not into psych
Linguistics you you only have the
hypothesis because you listen to people
you dare you need
psychoanalysis it's not into psycho
Linguistics well I think that we test
all our medications on rats and mice and
you can have a phobia in a mouse you can
have an anxiety disorder in the mouse
and other things this is what all
pharmacology is based on zero language
zero so when Lam says unconscious is
structured as a language what
unconscious is a vast space I have moral
memories of how my guad moves when I get
up from the chair I have phobic memories
I have all sorts of things in mind
conscious and I think it's a reduction
and it's a certain prism of looking at
things to say it's structured as a
language and language has multiple
structures you know so you know uh
English is structured differently than
Russian you know and so it's culturally
determined so I I I just think that it's
one of the possible Avenues of work I
think if we decode and decompose the
studies we can you know investigate the
important part is also falsifiability as
Brian nosik showed in 19
2015 36% of studies in Psychology are
reproducible vast majority of the
studies we do when an independent team
of researchers repeats it does not show
the repeated
result so a single study is also a data
point but but I'm saying that you know
uh theories are good hypothesis are good
research is good all of that is good but
but the point of my discussion was that
narrative fallacy exists it influences
clinical work let's be precise about it
I'm not saying let's not use language by
all means let's use language but we need
other things it's what I'm trying to
say wow lot to it um perhaps um each
people David you can unmute and then
each person can um make kind of some
closing
comments from here so David then Arian
then Albert then Le
unmute please David thank
you
um I think it's uh really
helpful that um the other
discussions
uh prepared questions from the
paper
um uh
I I fully agree about the limitations
of all of our models
and and
to have a research or experience-based
uh system
of uh monitoring things with patients
for instance Nancy
McWilliams um more recent
work uh talks about variables of that
describe this or that aspect of a given
patient that those are much
more uh meaningful
than
uh
uh a
descriptive
uh case formulation so I just wanted to
add that I like that part of the paper
including
NY um and that's all I'll
say thank you Albert then Aron then I'll
make some comments before
youi uh I'm not sure what I can say what
what I've already said before um I think
the discussion proves that the paper uh
uh opens up um a platform from great for
a great discussion maybe like to add a
closing remark uh maybe this is one of
like the defensive statements but um to
what extent is therapy a science in not
art that's that's a complicated question
but there you go thank you thank you
everybody um yes
um I still had one one one point uh in
in what I had prepared and and maybe I
can bring that point um in as a closing
remark um so Alexa you also say that the
key point of this paper is that we
should not be constrained in designing
clinical models by their need to fit the
limitations of our working
memory and it it comes to me that if the
clinical work is indeed um very much
more um
centered uh on on uh helping the patient
to hear uh what he says in all its
ambiguity which for me is an important
part of the work and next to the the
transference um then that that changes
also that that point uh because
um uh a big part of the clinical word
and is on the primary process level and
it is what is called free floating
attention and that does not uh weigh
upon the working memory because it's
actually um letting go of uh secondary
process control and inhibition it's the
inhibition which is very costly and um
so
uh yeah I understand uh that that that
your point is about a fallacy um but to
me the two points are
actually let's say obviated that
whatever the patient says uh it is
important and it makes the patient move
and um there by by using this angle um
you you're not weighed upon uh by
working memory uh at the level of your
working memory and
also but that would be another
another paper I guess in another
session I I do think that any technical
addition to therapy is actually um
counterproductive and I I I would I do
think that we need to replace any
medical or technical apparatus for
Psychotherapy to something which is
which which we dare to claim as
clinicians uh which is very much more uh
um human sciences and uh which is very
much more um about
uh the Dynamics of the mental apparatus
and and I think we should we should dare
to claim that that um Psychotherapy is
about uh uh these tools that that are
not in our model uh presence proximity
unconditionality unconditionality
patience of availability and listening
of course in an informed and in an
intelligent
way you you took a risk Alexa by
inviting me I'm
sorry it's so this is what I have to say
thank you it's awesome what you've
shared and complemented what he wrote
I'll just make a few points for
footnotes this reminds me a lot of
scientific pluralism there's
methodological pluralism there's
different measurements and how do we
even juxtapose something like as vast as
the unconscious with a brain region like
Alexi alluded to like what is that doing
in terms of how it plays out for people
already today um also as like a non
therapist I saw a lot of parallels
between the question or discussion does
the therapist have an
interpretation with does the organism
have a representation because people
debate well is it a representation if
it's aware or not aware of the
representation does it have a
representation or is it a representation
like David mentioned just sitting down
in the chair as a posture that then does
not use working memory or explicit
memory as just alluded to so I think
that the the interplay of the different
complex features of cognitive systems
and how expertise and experience and all
these other factors that you just
pointed to that last little piece like
proximity and availability
those factors that are going to go like
off the health record but they're part
of the actual moment that your training
is about so understanding what that is
and not letting it be like overly
reduced or or turned into measurements
is really um very rich and and important
discussion so again thank you Alexi for
bringing it together and everybody for
for joining on what is what's the last
word
Lexi well again I'm grateful to everyone
I like that it got a little more uh
Intense or heated or something and I
think they were just getting warmed up
this is the beginning of the
conversation maybe not the end of it I
welcome critique and commentary and
further discussions and uh I'm
completely fine with disagreements and
pluralism as David um Daniel you
mentioned uh um yeah it it's much more
nuanced than than what what I wrote
about but I I was opening hoping to even
talk about it because sometimes four uh
three journals uh refuse to publish the
paper you know one peer reviewer said
you know the best part of your paper is
where you cited fruit okay so meaning
everything else is completely useless
you know and so this is what I'm up
against and the fact that we're talking
about it is music to my arts and thank
you all very much one quick comment I
wanted to say about the tools I'm not
the kind of guy who says Let's dump the
humanity and introduce the tools let's
diagnose everything with AI That's not
the idea the idea is to Simply let's not
throw away information if I can get
additional information about the patient
if I know that they've tested their
thyroid last month and it's okay I'll
take it you know I I you know when
experiential people say I don't ask
questions I see what happens between me
and the patient I draw conclusions based
on that I think that's a flawed
technique because you need to know some
things I need to know if there was a
prior suicide attempt and and etc etc
and what medications are taking so I'll
take any and all information available
to me in whatever form visual auditory
whatever to help you know have a more
nuanced picture but again thank you all
very much I really appreciate it thank
you Daniel and uh yeah I think uh thank
you till
74.2 thanks thank you bye bye by bye
byee